Drew Coughlin

drew.coughlin@gmail.com | 415-501-0590 | https://drewsdata.github.io

Summary

Versatile data analyst and engineer passionate about helping people and organizations create insights and value from data. Excels at applying technical and organizational management skills and experience across the entire data analysis spectrum from business understanding through development and deployment.

Experience

Data Analyst Consultant

Paramount Global, Aug 2012 - Present

- Design and develop reporting solutions that enable consolidated data views from a variety of systems including Active Directory, Google Workspace, the internal corporate directory and Okta Identity Management
 - Technologies: R scripts, RStudio Shiny web app framework, Okta REST API, PostgreSQL DB, Google Workspace Calendar Python API
- Design and develop automated reports and dashboards that improve client's ability to manage SaaS spend and charge-back processes
 - Technologies: R scripts, Google Sheets, RStudio Shiny web framework, PostgreSQL DB, Okta REST API
- Design and develop ETL pipelines and automated processes that enabled email domain rebranding and unique email address validation
 - Technologies: R scripts, Google Workspace administration CLI scripts, PowerShell scripts
- Design and develop parameterized SQL reports and web apps that enable self-serve corporate directory hierarchy list creation for client activities including email list generation and product license assignments
 - Technologies: R scripts, SQL, RStudio Shiny web framework
- Design and develop ETL pipelines and automated processes supporting legal and electronic discovery processes for identifying and preserving Google Workspace accounts subject to legal hold
 - Technologies: R scripts, Google Workspace administration CLI scripts, Google Apps Script
- Designed and developed a BI solution for the Sales and Marketing team that eliminated a third-party analytics service and improved report accuracy
 - Technologies: Golang application, Google Sheets and a Google Analytics dashboard
- Developed a REST API service that enabled client's HRIS development team to maintain accurate employee record data
 - Technologies: Microsoft SQL DB, R language scripts

Risk Manager

Independent Derivatives Trader, Feb 2010 – Aug 2012

- Designed, developed and operated risk management and trading strategies based on statistical analysis of S&P
 500 futures market data
 - o Technologies: SQL, R scripts, RStudio Shiny web app framework
- Managed a leveraged trading fund that outperformed the underlying benchmark S&P 500 Index for two years
- Presented market data studies and performance analysis on futures options trading strategies and results

Manager

Bank of America, Nov 2003 - Feb 2010

- Managed analysts and developers that created and maintained tools and processes enforcing SEC and FINRA books and records requirements and reduced regulatory risk
- Developed business and technology requirements in consultation with legal, compliance and technology executives that governed electronic communications archival and surveillance
- Created electronic communication policies and guidelines governing multiple enterprise platforms serving over 100,000 workers

 Coordinated and developed executive level presentations on electronic communications regulatory controls and costs

Sales Engineer

Commerce One, Feb 2000 - Oct 2003

- Responsible for initial customer delivery acceptance of Commerce One marketplace applications during multi-million dollar licensing negotiations
- Designed and deployed software solutions using Commerce One marketplace applications to support sales, education and professional services teams
- Introduced virtual machine based application deployments that substantially reduced costs and expanded sales opportunities
- Produced webcasts for consultants and customers highlighting new application features
- Developed and delivered training and deployment programs for integration partners and customers

Education

Pennsylvania State University

Bachelor of Science - Management Information Systems Minor in Speech Communications